A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Office Files of E. Walter Coward, Jr. FA514
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Office Files of E. Walter Coward, Jr.
1977-1998
Rockefeller Archive Center
Coward, E. Walter
Ford Foundation
FA514
2.9 Cubic Feet 8 boxes (7 letter document containers and 1 half letter document containers)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. In 2019, two boxes of material from Accessions 2019:140 (Box 41094) and 2019:106 (Box 41093) were added to this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains grant files, chronological correspondence files, reports, meeting notes, and conference materials of E. Walter Coward, Jr.
Dr. Coward served as a program officer, deputy director, and director of the Rural Poverty and Resources program at the Ford Foundation between 1989 and 1995. In 1996, he became the senior director of the Asset Building and Community Development program in the Office of the Vice President, as well as acting director of Human Development and Reproductive Health program.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series:
1. RGA Grants
2. Chronological Correspondence
3. Conferences, Meetings, and Reports
Biographical / Historical
E. Walter Coward, Jr. served as a program officer, deputy director, and director of the Rural Poverty and Resources program at the Ford Foundation between 1989 and 1995. In 1996, he became the senior director of the Asset Building and Community Development program in the Office of the Vice President, as well as acting director of Human Development and Reproductive Health program. Before joining the Foundation, Dr. Coward was professor of Rural Sociology and Asian Studies at Cornell University. E. Walter Coward, Jr. retired from the Foundation in 1999.
The Ford Foundation's Assets program was a worldwide program concerned with reproductive health, economic development and community and resource development.
Agriculture -- International centers; Community development; Ford Foundation; Natural resources -- Management; Population research; Rural poverty and resourses
- RGA Grants, 1993-1996; 1
  Scope and Contents
  List of E. Walter Coward, Jr.'s RGA Grants (Grantee, Grant Program Action Number, and Length of Grant):
  American Farmland Trust (09200413), 1992 February 20-1995 December 31
  Arizona Board of Regents Acting for and on Behalf of Arizona State University (09400167), 1993 November 01-1999 December 31
  The Center for Rural Affairs (09000632)(09100810), 1990 January 01-1997 March 31
  Centro Internacional De Agricultura Tropical (09300793), 1993 January 01-1997 December 31
  Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz y Trigo (09300792), 1993 January 01-1997 December 31
  International Center for Research in Agroforestry (09300794), 1993 January 01-1997 December 31
  International Food Policy Research Institute (09300795), 1993 January 01-1997 December 31
  International Water Management Institute (09300796), 1993 January 01-1997 December 31
  World Bank (International Bank for Reconstruction and Development) (09200233), 1991 May 01-1996 March 31
  The Etv Endowment of South Carolina
  Fund for the International Conference of Agricultural Economists (09450113), 1993 October 01-1997 September 30
  High Country Foundation
  Community and Indian Legal Services, Inc. (09101023), 1991 July 01-1997 December 31
  Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security
  Public Voice for Food and Health Policy, Inc. (09201008), 1992 April 15-1994 April 14
  Pueblo of Zuni (09200833), 1992 May 01-1999 June 30
  Resources Development Foundation
  Rural Advancement Foundation International- Usa (09300357), 1993 January 01-1998 January 31
  Social Science Research Council (SSRC) (09450112), 1993 November 01-1997 November 01
  Tides Foundation (09400138), 1993 September 01-1997 April 30
  Tonantzin Land Institute (09200612), 1992 February 01-1994 May 31
  Trustees of Tufts University (09351311), 1993 August 01-1995 January 31
  University of Florida Foundation
  Henry A. Wallace Institute for Alternative Agriculture, Inc. (09300392), 1993 January 01-1996 December 31
  Winrock International Institute for Agricultural Development (09450488), 1994 January 01-1994 December 31
  World Resources Institute (09200506), 1991 October 01-1997 March 31
  - Grants A-Z, 1993 May-1994 April (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Grants A-Z, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Chronological Correspondence, 1995-1999; 2
  - Chron File A-Z, 1995 January-May (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Chron File A-Z, 1995 June-December (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Chron File A-Z, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Chron File A-Z, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    Interoffice Memos at the beginning of this file
  - Chron File A-Z, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 16, Box 4, Folder 17-18)
    Interoffice Memos at the beginning of the file
  - Chron File A-Z, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
- Conferences, Meetings, and Reports, 1977-1998; 3
  - The International Agricultural Research Centers and The Ford Foundation: A Report to the Ford Foundation by David E. Bell, 1981 October (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - People and Forests: A Report of a Ford Foundation Meeting on Social Forestry and Agro-Forestry, Naro Moru, Kenya, 1985 March 20-22 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Natural Resources Management Program Officer Consultation, Napa Valley, California, 1996 June 9-11 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - All Assets Staff Conference, San Antonio, Texas, 1998 November 11-13 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Walt's PowerPoint Presentation, San Antonio, Texas, 1998 November 12 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - A Review of the Ford Foundation's Work Related to Hispanics in the United States, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Assessment of the Ford Foundation's Grantmaking Related to Latinos in the United States: The Asset Building and Community Development Program, Edwin Melendez, PhD., 1997 July 21 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - CGIAR Mid-term Meeting, Jakarta, Indonesia, 1996 Information Booklet, 1996 May 20-24 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - CGIAR Research Agendas for Mid-term Meeting, 1996 May (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - CGIAR Mid-term Meeting, Istanbul, Turkey, 1992 May (Box 5, Folder 29, Box 6, Folder 30-32)
  - CGIAR Strategy, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Sections:
    Joint Program Review, 1992 April
    Letter to DGs, 1992 July
    DG Responses to July 1992 Letter
    Notes from Talks with DGs
    Notes from Trustees meeting, 1992 September
    Memo to Susan Berresford, 1993 January
    Letter to DGs, 1993 January
    DG Responses to 1993 January Letter
    Fax to DGs, 1993 March
    1993 Mid-Term Meeting
    International Centers Week - 1993
  - Biennial Program Review, 1995 March 27-April 7 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Biennial Program Review Text, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Asset Building and Community Development Program, Program Division Biennial Representatives and Directors Meeting, 1997 February (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Meeting of Trustee Committee on Assets, 1996 December (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - USDA National Commission on Small Farms Briefing Book, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Worldwide Rural Poverty and Resources Meeting, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1993 September 7-10 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Rural Poverty and Resources Program Review, 1993 November 23 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    Sections include:
    Agenda and Mission Statement
    Program Officer Memos
    Worldwide Work
    Who We Are: Human Development and Reproductive Health
    Budget Information Human Development and Reproductive Health FY 1998
  - A World in Motion: Working Globally, Program Division Leadership Meeting, 1998 February 16-20 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - The Asset Building Framework: Perspectives and Tools for a Global Program, Melvin L. Oliver, Assets Worldwide Meeting, San Antonio, Texas, 1998 November 11 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Ford Foundation Agriculture Support - History, 1977-1994 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Includes:
    Working Against Hunger (publication from 1978)
    Tables from 1977 Work in Agriculture report
    On-Farm Research in Eastern India: A Decennial Review, 1985-1994
    Staff lists, 1980-1981
    President's Review from the 1977 Annual Report
    List of Grants, 1956-1989
    World Agriculture and the Ford Foundation, Lowell Hardin
    Concept and Issues Paper - Agricultural Productivity (Report #011139)
  - Ford Foundation Agriculture Support - Notes and Memos, 1979-1995 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Note from original folder: page 2 - Coward report
  - Eric Holst/Eric Rusten Agriculture Project - Responses to Date, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Learning Organizations, 1990-1998 (Box 7, Folder 47, Box 8, Folder 48-51)